<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A learned and exceeding well-compiled vindication of liberty of religion: written by Junius Brutus in Latine, and translated into English by N.Y. who desires, as much as in him is, to do good unto all men: wherein these three following propositions are undenyably proved, and all objections to the contrary fully answered. 1. That if magistrates, in case of necessity, promise hereticks liberty of religion; they are bound to performe their promise after that necessity ceaseth. 2 That magistrates may with a safe conscience grant hereticks liberty of religion, and oblige themselves by an oath, or bond of assurance, to provide for their safety and security. 3. That magistrates ought to grant hereticks liberty of religion, and to oblige themselves by an oath, or bond of assurance, to provide for their safety and security.</title>
            <title>Vindiciae pro religionis libertate. English.</title>
            <author>Crell, Johann, 1590-1633.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1178_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208101</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 167:E1178[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A learned and exceeding well-compiled vindication of liberty of religion: written by Junius Brutus in Latine, and translated into English by N.Y. who desires, as much as in him is, to do good unto all men: wherein these three following propositions are undenyably proved, and all objections to the contrary fully answered. 1. That if magistrates, in case of necessity, promise hereticks liberty of religion; they are bound to performe their promise after that necessity ceaseth. 2 That magistrates may with a safe conscience grant hereticks liberty of religion, and oblige themselves by an oath, or bond of assurance, to provide for their safety and security. 3. That magistrates ought to grant hereticks liberty of religion, and to oblige themselves by an oath, or bond of assurance, to provide for their safety and security.</title>
                  <title>Vindiciae pro religionis libertate. English.</title>
                  <author>Crell, Johann, 1590-1633.</author>
                  <author>N. Y. translator.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Junius Brutus = Johann Crell.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119385:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A LEARNED And exceeding well-compiled Vindication of</hi> Liberty of <hi>RELIGION: Written by</hi> Junius Brutus <hi>in Latine, And Tranſlated into Engliſh by</hi> N. Y. <hi>who deſires, as much as in him is, to do good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men: Wherein theſe three following Propoſitions are undenyably proved, and all Objections to the contrary fully Anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That if Magiſtrate, in caſe of neceſſity, promiſe Hereticks Liberty of <hi>Religion;</hi> they are bound to performe their promiſe after that neceſſity ceaſeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That Magiſtrates may with a ſafe Conſcience grant He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks Liberty of <hi>Religion,</hi> and oblige themſelves by an Oath, or Bond of aſſurance, to provide for their ſafety and ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Magiſtrates ought to grant Hereticks Liberty of <hi>Religion,</hi> and to oblige themſelves by an Oath, or Bond of aſſurance, to provide for their ſafety and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed in the Year</hi> 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119385:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119385:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have long ſince moſt earneſtly deſired <hi>(Chriſtian Reader)</hi> that as there is a harmony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in diſcords of Muſick, ſo likewiſe there might be a ſweet ſympathy and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſtian charity,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:3"/> and civill friendſhip in the mindes of all men, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any diſcords of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions touching matters of Religion. And ſurely the beſt courſe that I can take to accompliſh my deſire, is to convince thy conſcience that liberty of Religion is lawfull, and allowable; which I am fully perſwaded this ſhort Treatiſe that I tranſlate is able to perform, if ſo be thou ſhalt reſolve to reade it over with a minde free from prejudice and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection:
<pb facs="tcp:119385:3"/> For I am ſure that what of any moment can be ſpoken for, or objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt liberty of Religion, that is here both ſtrongly urged, and fully anſwered. I dare ſay that every ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and equall judge will grant, that he never ſaw as yet any Tract, of the ſame length, concerning the ſame Subject, of like worth and eſtimation with this. VVouldeſt thou have ſtrength of Argument, good method, neat compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:4"/> perſwaſive cloquence: All theſe conſpire and meet together here. If any ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh ſeem to be in this both ſolid and beautifull ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, as it is ſet forth in an Engliſh dreſſe, I am the cauſe thereof, and not the Author. Be not offended <hi>(Gentle Reader)</hi> becauſe thou ſeeſt the name of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> and <hi>Heretiques</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to them in this Treatiſe, to whom it is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally given by the Papiſts, but rather be pleaſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:4"/> that liberty of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is here defended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the adverſaries there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, even upon their owne termes and conditions. For certainly no ſtronger proof can be brought for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and right of liberty in Religion, than to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that Papiſts, or other Sects may, and ought to grant it, although it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be true in it ſelfe, which they conceite of themſelves, and all other men, who differ from them
<pb facs="tcp:119385:5"/> in religion. If thou ask me the queſtion whether it will neceſſarily follow, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants ought as well as Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to grant freedome of religion. I anſwer, yes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly. For Papiſts have ſome plea for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the denyall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, becauſe they believe, though falſly, That the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their Church is infallible, and therefore that ſhe cannot erre in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſpirits, in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:5"/> and in her determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Controverſies. But Proteſtants, who hold that the authority of the Church is fallible, that the greateſt Aſſembly of Divines may erre, and oftentimes have erred in their judgement of the ſpirits, in their interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Scriptures, and in their deciſions of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies; and therefore allow the common people to ſearch the Scriptures, and to try the ſpirits by them as the only Iudge, or rather, to
<pb facs="tcp:119385:6"/> ſpeak properly, as the only Rule, cannot have any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable pretence to deny it: unleſſe they will now at length renounce their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and deſtroy the grounds of their Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſeparation from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tends this diſcourſe? to ſhew that a better Treatiſe, than this which I tranſlate, could not be ſet forth, to prove that <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are as much obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> if not more,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:6"/> to grant a toleration of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to their Subjects. So that now (judicious <hi>Reader)</hi> thou mayſt clearly perceive that notwithſtanding thoſe names of <hi>Catholiques</hi> and <hi>Heretiques</hi> thou meetſt with in every Leafe and vein al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of this Tract, the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it, and the anſwers in it againſt objections, war as ſtrongly and directly for us in this Kingdome againſt our Proteſtant adverſaries, in the cauſe of toleration and liberty of Religion, as
<pb facs="tcp:119385:7"/> it doth for any Sect of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> againſt any adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries whatſoever: and that when thou haſt read it, there is not more promiſed in the Title page, then is made good in the Diſcourſe thereof. Thus being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of my Authors brevity, and unwilling to offend thy patience, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt. N. Y.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:119385:7"/>
            <p> THE name of Catholicks and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks is attributed to them, in this Treatiſe, to whom it is wont to be given by the Church of Rome, that the Controverſie may be ended, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding without any prejudice, or hurt to the Cauſe it ſelfe: For when as they which diſſent from the Church of Rome, deſire a ſafe and ſound civill peace may be allowed them, either it is to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that they are not Hereticks; or that although they were, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the members of the Church of Rome ought to live peaceably with them. The former Controverſie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be determined, unleſſe the one ſide,
<pb facs="tcp:119385:8"/> overcome by the Arguments of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, condeſcend to their opinion. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it would be tedious to expect here an end thereof. But the latter may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily he decided, yea and ought to be, even whilſt the former ſtands in debate, and of that only this Treatiſe takes upon it to diſcourſe. Therefore the Author of this Treatiſe puts the caſe, as if they were ſuch, which diſſent from the Church of Rome, as they account them; but hee doth no more affirm it, then believe the truth thereof.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119385:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Catholiques ought to grant them, whom they deem Hereticks, the liberty of Religion which they promiſe, even then, when they could ſuppreſſe them without any damage, or hurt to themſelves.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Catholique Religion permits freedome of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be granted Hereticks, and proviſion to be made for their ſafety and ſecurity, even for the future, without any limitation of time, when they cannot be ſuppreſſed and deſtroyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out detriment to the Church: both the writings of learned men, and practiſe it ſelf doth teſtifie: From hence it followeth, the ſame Religion ought alwayes to grant, that afterwards free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Religion hath once been promiſed He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, it ſhould not then be taken from them, when they may be ſubverted, and borne downe without any damage to the Church.</p>
            <p>For when Catholicks give aſſurance unto He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, that they will not oppreſſe, nor moleſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119385:9"/> them for Religions ſake, they promiſe to do them no miſchief then eſpecially, when they ſhall have opportunity to do it: For why ſhould they promiſe to abſtain from doing that, which either they cannot do at all, or w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they cannot without much hurt and damage to themſelves? Therefore whereas promiſes, and faithfull deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing require, that what is ſpoken ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; it muſt needs follow, that Catholiques, if they deſire to avoid the crime of treachery and falſe dealing, ought even then to ſuffer and tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Heretiques, when they could overwhelm them without bringing any trouble unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And ſurely if conſcience will ſuffer them to aſſure Heretiques that they ſhall enjoy liberty of Religion amongſt them, without any limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time, or expreſſely even for perpetuity; their conſcience alſo will allow them, yea re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to make that liberty ſafe and ſecure to Heretiques conſtantly, although they might conveniently be ſuppreſt. Which that it may be made more clear and evident, we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the nature of Covenants, and bonds of aſſurance. When any one makes a bargain, and bond of aſſurance with another, he promiſeth to do that, which otherwiſe he could without any loſſe to himſelf, yea perhaps even to his own profit, omit, and do the contrary. And he which deſires ſecurity may be given him, requires an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to perform that to himſelf, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he had liberty to leave undone, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the intermiſsion thereof might be more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119385:9"/> beneficiall and pleaſing to him. For covenants and agreements were deviſed, to the end pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion might be made for the ſafety of our own intereſts and conveniences, even then when no externall force or damage can compell the other party, either to abſtain from doing wrong, or to perform that benefit and good turn he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth: for truth and faithfulneſſe in promiſes ought to prevail as much with us as compulſion. Wherefore whileſt Catholiques give aſſurance unto Heretiques that they ſhall enjoy freedome of Religion for the time to come, and they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſire aſſurance of them: that they aſſure, and theſe deſire to be aſſured of, is, that for the future they ſhall be ſecure from receiving any damage by the Catholiques, when it might be profitable to them to ſubvert and deſtroy Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques. But if Conſcience doth not allow Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques to deal thus with Heretiques, alſo it will not permit them to make ſuch Agreements as I have ſpoken of, at any time with Heretiques, much leſſe to confirm them with the holy reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of an oath. From whence it will certainly follow, that all thoſe Catholiques have greatly ſinned, who ever made with Heritiques ſuch Conventions: and that not only other Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Doctors have erred, which approved of ſuch Covenants when neceſsity preſt them to it, but even the very Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelf, head of the Catholique Church, who doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne thoſe writings ſet forth by the Jeſuites themſelves, in which ſuch Agreements are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119385:10"/> Furthermore it would follow from thence, that a neceſsity lieth upon Heretiques, if they would regard their own ſafety, of plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and endeavouring alwayes, where and when they can, to deſtroy Catholiques utterly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they would be contented for a while to live quietly amongſt them: becauſe they know that Catholiques, when they ſhall get a fit oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to oppreſſe and kill them, cannot only make uſe of it with a ſafe conſcience, but alſo that they cannot but put it in execution with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violence to their conſcience; and that by vertue of their Religion they are conſtrained to ſuppreſſe them, notwithſtanding any promiſe whatſoever: becauſe ſurely thoſe promiſes, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever confirmed with oaths, become then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and of none effect, when Heretiques may be quelled and ſubverted without prejudice and perill to the Church. Therefore unleſſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques be reſolved to betray their own lives and fortunes, they ought not to ſpare Catholiques, if they can overcome them: moreover, if there be any hopes to prevail by taking up of Arms, they ought to lay hold on them, and not to ſtay till in proceſſe of time, and by ſome ſudden change, they become altogether unequall in number and ſtrength unto the Catholiques; but to ſet preſently upon them, and run rather the hazard of a doubtfull war, than expect a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain deſtruction from them. But if theſe things ſeem ſtrange and abſurd to Catholiques, and they make ſuch agreements without any ſcruple
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119385:10"/> of conſcience, and have the conſent of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers to do ſo, in thoſe Kingdoms, Provinces, and Common-wealths where they are not ſtrong enough to contend with Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques: it is neceſſary altogether that conſcience ſhould permit them alſo to ſtand to thoſe cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, when it is expedient and profitable for Catholiques to break them. And verily, if Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques make ſuch like agreements at any time, that they may prevent the bringing of ſome diſcommodity and dammage to their Church: they are bound alſo afterwards to remit and let go that benefit, which they may hope to gain by the downfall of Heretiques; For it is juſt and requiſite, that he which reaped formerly profit by conditions and compacts, ſhould alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuffer ſome inconvenience and diſprofit, which bargains and agreements may bring upon him: although there is indeed no inconvenience or diſcommodity herein, as ſhall be proved very largely in the following Chapter. There remains yet thus much to be ſaid, That by the law of Nature thou oughteſt not to do that to another man, which thou wouldeſt not have done to thy ſelf: And on the contrary, we are enjoyned even by the Law of God and Chriſt, to <hi>deale with other men, as we would be dealt with our ſelves,</hi> Mat. 8. 7, 12. But who amongſt the Catholiques would be willing and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if Heretiques, in caſe of ſome urgent neceſſity, had granted them liberty in their dominions, That when that Neceſsity is taken away, they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119385:11"/> ſhould lay violent hands on them, and deprive them of their freedom? Might they not call that perfidious and treacherous dealing? and very juſtly. Why therefore do either they themſelves deal ſo with other men, or hold it fit and lawfull to be done? I do not think indeed that the moderate ſort of men amongſt the Catholiques will ſay as much, which I will forthwith inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and declare: yet notwithſtanding it is apparent that ſome are ſo tranſported with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt Heretiques, that they ſeem to hold, no promiſe or oath at all is to be made good by Catholiques unto Heretiques; and the ſame ſpeech to be applied againſt Heretiques, which <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpoke concerning theeves and plunderers, in his 3. Book of <hi>Offices,</hi> to wit, that it is no guile to keep back from them that price and ranſome which a man promiſeth to redeem his life, No, although he ſwore that he would bring it to them: And if a Catholique hath bound himſelf by oath to perform any thing to Heretiques, he may take up that ſaying of <hi>Euripides, I have ſworn with my tongue, but I keep my mind free from the oath.</hi> For a Heretique is the common enemy of all mankinde, as much as a Robber, with whom no good man can have any fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and commerce, and ſurely make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, nor oblige himſelf by oath unto him. Yea, a Heretique is worſe than a Thief, becauſe this man only kils mens bodies, but he deſtroyes their ſcules. If this be ſo, Heretiques had need take great heed, and beware that they do not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119385:11"/> at any time believe any Catholiques promiſes, covenants, leagues, and oathes; but take them to be meer ſnares and ginnes, invented only to beguile and circumvent them. But furthermore, what a horrible thing is it, and unbeſeeming a man, eſpecially a Chriſtian, to affirme, that any man may ſwear with his tongue, and reſerve his minde free from the oath; that is, ſwear in words, that he will do ſuch a thing, which hee hath not only no purpoſe to perform, but even judges it a wicked thing to be performed by him: What now will be eſteemed holy, what inviolable, what ſincere and undefiled, if it ſhall be lawfull to deceive with the reverend feare of an oath? And is there any Chriſtian man to be found, who doth not ſtick to aſſert and avouch, that it is lawfull to take that holy and reverend name of God in vain, and to confirm therewith a lie, and a very ungodly matter? It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that if a man ſhall promiſe any thing with an oath, which cannot be performed without the guilt of ſin and impiety, that oath ought to be broken: but likewiſe it is as true, that we muſt never confirm that with an oath, in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment whereof we muſt needs commit wickedneſſe; and he ought to be very ſorrowfull and penitent, who even through errour and want of judgement eſtabliſheth a wicked matter with an oath; ſo far is it from being lawfull for any man to make good ſuch an oath, which under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the haynouſneſſe thereof. For no man truly ſhould engage himſelf, no not by a ſimple
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119385:12"/> promiſe, to perpetrate and effect a wicked mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, much leſſe to ratifie an ungodly promiſe with an oath. Certainly that man, which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly ſhall do ſo, is both a perjured perſon, and guilty alſo of a twofold impiety: Firſt, becauſe he promiſed an unrighteous thing knowingly; and then becauſe he made no ſcruple to confirm an ungodly promiſe with a moſt holy thing, and abuſed the reverend name of God, to the end he might have a fit occaſion to defraud and beguile others. No neceſſity can excuſe him in this point. For a Chriſtian man ſhould rather die a thouſand deaths, than condeſcend to ſuch a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full oath. Therefore that ſpeech of <hi>Euripides</hi> is unjuſt, and proceeded from a heatheniſh impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>I ſwore with my tongue, I reſerve my mind free from the oath:</hi> That of <hi>Cicero</hi> is as bad, <hi>That the ranſom is not to be brought in to a thief, which thou ſhalt promiſe him with an oath to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem thy life.</hi> Either thou muſt not ſwear at all, if thou haſt no intent to perform thy oath, if thou thinkeſt it diſhoneſty to make it good, much more if thou thinkeſt it a ſinfull thing to be done; or if thy conſcience tell thee thou mayeſt lawfully ſwear, thy oath ſhould be truly kept. For neither doth God ſuffer himſelf to be deluded, nor him to go ſcotfree, which taketh his name in vain. And obſerve I pray, how far the judgement of God himſelf, and pious men, differs from the opinion of <hi>Euripides</hi> and <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</hi> God had commanded the Iſraelites in times paſt, <hi>To deſtroy the Inhabitants of the Land of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 33. 52.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119385:12"/> 
               <hi>Canaan, and to make an univerſall ſlaughter of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 7. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>them, not to make any covenant with them, nor to have any compaſſion on them, and that by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>reaſon of the impious idolatry of thoſe nations, and other moſt grievous crimes and enormities.</hi> The Gibeonites, which were a part of them that were born and bred in that land, went to <hi>Ioſua</hi> and the reſt of the people, faining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be no inhabitants of that land, but to come from a far country; and prevailed by this wile with <hi>Joſua</hi> and the reſt of the Princes, to make a league with them in the name of all the People, and to eſtabliſh it with an oath. What would they have ſaid in this caſe, which hold it not lawfull for Leagues, Covenants, and Oaths to be kept with Heretiques, although heretiques ſhall uſe no craft to over-reach them, but ſhall tranſact all things openly and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſunne, or rather in the ſight of God? would they not have cryed out, that this wicked covenant was contrary to Gods expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement? and beſides procured by deceit, and therefore voyd, of none effect, and utterly to be broken. That <hi>Joſua</hi> indeed, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the people ſwore, but as it were upon ſome certain condition, as if ſo be thoſe things were true which the Gibeonites had ſpoken, that is, if they were not ſome Inhabitants of the land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> But ſeeing that is falſe, the People are not bound to obſerve their oath. But <hi>Joſua</hi> and the Princes of the people were of a quite contrary mind, and the People after
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119385:13"/> their inſtruction, and laſtly God himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his judgement to the contrary: For, three dayes after, they perceived their fraud, and yet notwithſtanding they ſpared them. And when as all the people murmured againſt the Princes, they made them anſwer, <hi>We have ſworne unto them by the Lord God of Iſrael, and therefore we may not touch them,</hi> Joſ. 9. 19. And moreover God himſelf approved and confirmed this oath, neither permittted it in proceſſe of time to be violated. For when as a few ages after, <hi>Saul</hi> had killed ſome of them, God viſited all the people of Iſrael with famine, neither could his wrath be appeaſed for this deed of <hi>Saul,</hi> before ſeven of his ſonnes and nephewes were hanged. But if God would have the Iſraelites to perform that league and covenant which was made with the Gibeonites contrary to his own manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, and gotten beſides by deceit; why ſhould not thoſe leagues and oaths be kept with Heretiques, which they purchaſed without any guile of theirs? when as they have no command from God either to puniſh or kill them, much leſſe ſo cleare as that, which the Iſraelites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to deſtroy the Canaanites, of which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more ſhall be ſaid in that which followes. But it is moſt unjuſt, for thoſe men to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as bad as thieves and robbers, or even worſe than them, and to be ranked amongſt thoſe men with whom no fellowſhip or ſociety may be entertained, no promiſe made and kept: which know not themſelves to be heretiques,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119385:13"/> and would not be ſuch if they knew it; but moſt ſtrongly believe that they hold opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of Religion, which are true, pious, and altogether agreeable to the word of God, neither do, nor purpoſe to do wrong to any man. For thieves know they invade other mens rights, and that they ſinne againſt the law of nature which is engraven in their hearts, and are not ignorant they do that which is evill; and that which is of moſt force in this point, they diſturb, violate, and deſtroy the peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of other men: Therefore when as they offend againſt the laws of a commonwealth, the puniſhments thereof are juſtly inflicted on them, &amp; they are puniſhed by the Magiſtrate as break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of that common peace, which God ordained him to preſerve. But Heretiques, which live peaceably with other men, and deſire to live ſo for the future, neither know that they ſinne, nor that they commit any thing againſt the lawes of civill ſociety. But if that reaſon were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, whereby it is alleadged, that they deſtroy mens ſoules, which they are utterly ignorant that they do, yea are fully perſwaded that they do not: then it would prevaile as much againſt infidels, ſuch as <hi>Jewes</hi> are, whom notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Catholiques ſuffer to abide in their domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and againſt <hi>Mahometans,</hi> whom they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to live in ſome parts of <hi>Polonia.</hi> But if thou replieſt, that Infidels do not ſpread abroad their poyſon amongſt others, as the Heretiques do: That I may paſſe over with ſilence, that even
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119385:14"/> Infidels, if they can, will draw other men over to their opinions; and that they do not hinder it from comming to paſſe, but it happeneth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reaſon of Chriſtians conſtancie, or the contempt and abject condition of <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> in theſe countries, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with the ſame venemous conceits they infect their children. Who can have the heart to tolerate a Jew, or other infidel in his dominion, that would ſlay his children? yet the Catholiques do, although they deſtroy their childrens ſoules. It is evident therefore, that they which unwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly deſtroy mens ſoules, as Heretiques are thought to do, are not to be dealt withall in like meaſure with thoſe, much leſſe to be more grievouſly puniſhed, which kill their bodies. If this argument were of force, all Harlots were to be deſtroyed: for what? do not they deſtroy mens ſoules, whilſt they intice them to commit fornication? Doth not Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirme, that <hi>Whoremongers ſhall not poſſeſſe the kingdome of God?</hi> And <hi>Iohn,</hi> that <hi>whoremongers ſhall have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 9. Gal. 5. 19. Rev. 21. 8. &amp; 22. 15.</note> 
               <hi>their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone?</hi> And yet Catholique Princes, and Common-wealths in <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and elſwhere ſuffer them to live under their protection: and the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not expell them thence; when as they offend alſo againſt civill honeſty, and tranſgreſſe the lawes of chaſtity and modeſty, which are ingrafted in the minds of all men, but eſpecially of the female ſexe by nature. Why therefore ſhould Heretiques, who
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119385:14"/> neither break the lawes of nature, nor civill honeſty, and do not ſo eaſily allure mens minds to imbrace their errours, as harlots do to a wanton love of themſelves, be worſe dealt withall, becauſe they deſtroy mens ſoules? why ſhould they be accounted ſuch, with whom no fellowſhip may be admitted, no rules of juſtice, no friendſhip obſerved? ſeeing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they live honeſtly, injure no man, yea en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to deſerve the good will of all men, and as much as in them lies, to live peaceably with all men. For, that I may caſt the whole matter as it were into this ſhort concluſion: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever obſerve the rules of civill ſociety, neither diſturb the peace and tranquility of other men, they cannot by any juſt authority be ejected out of a civill ſociety, neither ſhould they in any wiſe be denied peace and ſecurity. Wherefore, when as Heretiques are in every reſpect thus qualified and diſpoſed, they ſhould neither be baniſhed from a civill communion, nor peace and quietneſſe be denied them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119385:15"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Catholiques may with a ſafe Conſcience allow Heretiques freedome of Religion, and give them Security for it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>MAny are afraid, eſpecially when no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity compels them to it, to grant He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques freedom of Religion, and to take order for their ſafety: becauſe to do ſo, would be to ſhew a liking and approbation of hereſie, and to give them authority to propagate and diſperſe abroad their peſtilent and deadly Errors. And yet notwithſtanding, the ſame men, without any ſcruple of conſcience allow <hi>Jewes,</hi> and in ſome places <hi>Mahometans</hi> (as I have ſaid before) liberty of Religion, and give them a bond of aſſurance for their ſafety: What, do they perhaps by this means approve of the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> errors, and of their blaſphemies againſt Chriſt? To approve of; and not to ſuppreſſe by force; are two different things. Neither verily haſt thou any cauſe to ſay, that the caſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, of which ſort <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> are, is not the ſame with that of Heretiques: for that difference which is between them, is of no moment in this point, where the queſtion only is, whether or no heretiques errors be approved of, by granting them liberty of Religion. For
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119385:15"/> in this matter the caſe of heathens and hereticks is one and the ſame: But as for that power they ſpeak of, which may be given heretiques by granting them liberty, if they mean ſuch a power by which Hereſie may be approved of and judged good and honeſt; ſuch a priviledge Catholiques can neither give Heretiques, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do Heretiques deſire them to do it, but it is a licence only of indempnity, and of being free from civill puniſhment, which even he may give which doth not only not allow of hereſie, but alſo very much abhorres and diſallowes it. So a civill indempnity &amp; immunity is granted drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and covetous men; for who puniſheth them for thoſe vices? although both ſorts ſinne both grievouſly themſelves, and do hurt by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and much dammage redounds by both vices unto other men, and oftentimes unto the commonmealth. But who would ſay, that thou approveſt of their vices, and giveſt them autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to commit thoſe ſinnes, which thou canſt not; if thou ſhalt promiſe them in good earneſt that thou wilt not puniſh them, if ſo be they do no wrong to other men. Many Princes do great wrong to their Subjects, and nevertheleſſe they are not liable to any civill puniſhment for it, and their liberty would be violated if thou ſhouldeſt puniſh them for it. And truly that happens in every Dominion, eſpecially that which is Abſolute, that the Magiſtrate ſhould go unpuniſhed for that injury which he commits againſt him, over whom he hath abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119385:16"/> Now that liberty of Religion which is allowed heretiques, requires nothing elſe but that thou ſhouldſt not hinder them by any force from attending their Religion, from exerciſing, profeſſing, defending, and endeavouring to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate it without any violence; nor that thou do any evill or hurt unto them for it, but referre the whole buſineſſe to God, that he himſelfe may puniſh them when he pleaſeth: That thou leaveſt it to the Catholique Church, that it may as ſtrongly as it can oppoſe them with ſpirituall weapons, in which it is prevalent, whether they be miracles, or reaſons and arguments: more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if thou ſo think fit, that ſhe may correct them with cenſures meerly Eccleſiaſticall; I ſay meerly eccleſiaſticall, not civill, leſt violent hands be laid upon their bodies or goods. When as Chriſtians in the primitive times lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Jews and heathens, they truly did them no hurt, neither puniſhed, or endeavoured to puniſh them with any civill puniſhment. Now they might bind themſelves by oath and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to do that, which they did really perform; yet nevertheleſſe no man ſhall have cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſay that they approved of the Iewes and Pagans wicked and blaſphemous errors, or that they gave them ſuch a licence to diſſeminate and promote their errors, which no Chriſtian can with a good conſcience. But if thou alleadgeſt that the Chriſtians of that Age could not do otherwiſe, becauſe they were not ſtrong enough to deal with Infidels; but would have done o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119385:16"/> if ſo be that they had been ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to contend with them. What elſe ſhalt thou hereby affirme, but that thoſe Primitive Chriſtians were like ſerpents in the boſome of Infidels, who ſo long abſtained from hurting them, as they had not power to do it, yet ready ſo ſoon as they ſhould have a fit opportunity to afflict and repreſſe them. By this means thou wilt make their charity, deſire of peace, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience towards Infidels, fained and counterfeit, which would forthwith break out into cruelty and war againſt them, when Chriſtians ſhould begin to put confidence in their own ſtrength. Hereby Infidels will have very great cauſe given them to plot and contrive an univerſall ſlaughter of Chriſtians; for becauſe they muſt expect and look for a moſt certain deſtruction from them, notwithſtanding any meekneſſe and patience whatſoever which is outwardly pretended.</p>
            <p>Seeing theſe things are very abſurd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ungodly to be uttered, and injurious to the piety of thoſe holy men which profeſſe Chriſt and ſuffer martyrdome for his ſake: we muſt needs conclude, that the primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians would certainly have tolerated Infidels, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they might have been able to ſuppreſſe them. And moreover, That to tolerate Errors in other men, ſo far forth, as not to perſecute and afflict them with Civil dammages and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, whom thou mighteſt quell by force; is not to approve of Errors, be they never ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent and ungodly. Conſequently alſo, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119385:17"/> for Chriſtians to grant them ſuch a kind of freedom and indempnity, which nouriſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend wicked Errors: for if it be lawfull for thee to make good ſuch an indempnity and impunity unto thoſe, which cheriſh and foment ungodly and deſtructive Errors; it will be lawfull alſo for thee to give them licence for it, that is, to promiſe them and give them good aſſurance that thou wilt as much as in thee lies, preſerve them harmleſſe, and that thou wilt not bring any damage or puniſhment upon them for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies ſake, or take order that they be ſo dealt withall: but rather on the contrary wilt hinder them which are under thy authority and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and to whom thou canſt preſcribe lawes, from doing them any miſchief. For what thou mayeſt lawfully perform, that is, juſtly and without ſinne; even that alſo thou mayeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige thy ſelf to perform, and give another man ſecurity that thou wilt.</p>
            <p>But ſome object that of <hi>Paul, Be ye not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally yoked together with unbelievers; For what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe? and what communion hath light with darkneſſe? and what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? or what part hath he that believeth, with an Infidel? and what agreement hath the temple of God with idols?</hi> But this ſpeech doth not concern a civill peace or conjunction, as that is between members of the ſame common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, governed by the ſame lawes. Becauſe both S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, and all other Chriſtians in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119385:17"/> that Age, entertained ſuch a peace and concord with Infidels, both Jews and Gentiles, amongſt whom they lived. Moreover, the ſame Apoſtle elſwhere commanded Chriſtians to <hi>live in peace,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ro. 12. 18. Heb. 12. 14. 1 Cor. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>as much as in them lieth, with all men.</hi> And wrote expreſly to the ſame Corinthians: <hi>I wrote unto you in an epiſtle, not to be mixed</hi> (that is, to have no familiarity) <hi>with fornicators; Yet not altogether with the fornicators of this world,</hi> (that is, Infidels) <hi>or with the covetous, or extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, or with idolaters, for then muſt ye needs go out of the world, &amp;c.</hi> There he evidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Believers to have converſation with Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels and Idolators, to trade, yea even to eat with them, as appeares by the following words. And is not even now a civill peace admitted with the <hi>Iewes?</hi> Are not Lawes eſtabliſhed for their ſecurity? Are not Leagues and other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions made by Chriſtian Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, and by the Kingdome it ſelfe of <hi>Polonia,</hi> with <hi>Mahometans?</hi> Therefore the words of S. <hi>Paul</hi> do not ſpeak of a civill ſociety and friendſhip, and other ſuch like agreements; but of another more near and inward affinity, from which they may abſtain, who entertain a civill friendſhip with one another, and take great delight in living peaceably together, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing courteſie, and doing many good offices to one another, upon every occaſion that is offered. Verily Chriſtians ought to do thſe friendly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices unto all men, although more eſpecially to them which are of the <hi>houſhold of faith,</hi> As the <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119385:18"/> ſame <hi>Paul</hi> ſignifieth, who will not have them to be yoked with Infidels.</p>
            <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers bring another Argument. <hi>If he ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 17.</note> 
               <hi>neglect to hear the Church, let him be unto thee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an heathen man, and a Publican.</hi> But this place doth not prove that at all, which they would have it: For Chriſt will have us deal with him that will not hear the Church, as the Jews were wont to deal with Heathens and Publicans. But the Jews did not expell Heathens and Publicans the common-wealth or city; they did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them, they did them no ſhrewd turn, or inflict a civill puniſhment upon them: only they were not wont to have a familiar conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with them, and refuſed, although they were invited, to come unto their tables: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe they had communication for buying and ſelling with them, and dealt with them in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and private affaires? and if they came into their houſes, they did not drive them out, and truly they did not keep them from their tables if ſo be they would needs eat together with them. Beſides, Heretiques and Infidels are not ſpoken of in this place, but Believers only, which ſhall ſinne againſt their brother, and will not acknowledge their fault, after they have been both privately, and publiquely admoniſhed and rebuked by the Church for it. Their caſe is not the ſame, which belong not to the Church, of which ſort are Heretiques, eſpecially ſuch as are borne of hereticall parents.</p>
            <p>Some object that alſo of S. John, <hi>If there com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Joh. 10, 11.</note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119385:18"/> 
               <hi>any unto you, and bring you not this doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed; for he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evill deeds.</hi> But firſt of all, it is one thing to receive a man into our houſe, and to bid him God ſpeed; and another thing to drive him out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingdome or city, and to lay vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands on his body and goods. That in thoſe dayes, believers could do; this they could not; and therefore <hi>Iohn</hi> commands them not to do this, but that only. Moreover, mention is made there only of ſeducers, whom he cals Antichriſts, which did not confeſſe that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh,</hi> As appears by the foregoing words, and may be perceived by many places of the firſt Epiſtle. But there are not ſuch Heretiques in theſe times, as deny that: ſo far is it from being true, that Heretiques of theſe times may be caſt into the number of thoſe Seducers, which endeavour contrary to the manifeſt truth, and the conſcience of their mind, to lead others into ſuch a damnable error. Laſtly, in ſuch a caſe only <hi>Iohn</hi> forbids us to receive them into our houſes, or to bid them God ſpeed, when as they come unto us to perſwade and convert us to their Religion; not when they agitate civill or private matters, and deſire commerce with us is members of the ſame Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Many urge that alſo for an argument againſt liberty of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligion, That God commanded in former times, falſe Prophets, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe alſo that revolted to the worſhipping of falſe gods,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119385:19"/> to be killed. But firſt of all, it is one thing to be a Heretique, and another thing to be a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or to decline to the worſhip of falſe gods. They which now adayes are termed he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, worſhip none beſides that true God, creator of heaven and earth, and Jeſus Chriſt their Saviour; but only they hold different opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions from the Catholiques concerning him, or about ſacred matters, and ſuch as pertain to the worſhip of that true God and Jeſus Chriſt. Therefore they have not declined to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of falſe gods, ſo far is it from being juſt that they ſhould be reckoned amongſt falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which perſwade other men to ſuch a hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crime: for thoſe men only were to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted falſe Prophets, which endeavoured to perſwade, that they ſpake by inſpiration of ſome deity, and that their ſayings were to be eſteemed oracles; which the Heretiques of this age in no wiſe do. But that, that law of God made againſt falſe prophets, and worſhippers of falſe gods, is not intended againſt thoſe, who otherwiſe held the Law of God was to be kept, but were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with ſome other error, that may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhew, becauſe that in former times among the Jewes, who were affected with a vehement love and zeal toward the Law, Heretiques not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding were tolerated. And verily even in the time of Chriſt himſelfe, and long before him, there were Sadduces, which denied that there were Angels and Spirits, and were ſtiffe oppoſers of the Reſurrection of the dead, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119385:19"/> (as the Catholique Doctors report) rejected all the Prophets beſides <hi>Moſes.</hi> And although the greateſt part both of the People and the Rulers believed them to erre exceedingly, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe they were not expelled the city, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exempted from being Magiſtrates, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any other civil office; yea they were not hindred from comming to the Temple or the Synagogues. Why therefore ſhould it be thought fit that Heretiques in theſe times ſhould be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, by vertue of that law made againſt falſe Prophets, and worſhippers of falſe gods? It may be added for a further proofe, That they which in old time ſeduced the people from the true God, to the worſhip of falſe gods, or fell off of their own accord to it, could not but know that they did that which was againſt the expreſſe law of God; becauſe the law of God enacted againſt that matter, was ſo cleare and manifeſt, that no man could be ignorant of the meaning thereof. But they which now a dayes paſſe for heretiques, know not, that they do, or believe any thing contrary to the Law, and other Oracles divine; and if they knew it, would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon all ſuch opinions in Religion, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe falſe Prophets, and Apoſtates alſo, were in far greater fault, than Heretiques of this Age are: and therefore it doth not forthwith hold true, that theſe men ought to ſuffer the ſame puniſhment which God commanded to be executed againſt them. And thus much alſo may be addtd, That in thoſe dayes Prophecies were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119385:20"/> frequent and in force almoſt continually among the people of Iſrael, by which evident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were ever and anon publiſhed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God and his will, ſo as no man could be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant what he ought to hold concerning God and his worſhip, unleſſe he would purpoſely ſhut his eyes, and wink at noon-day. But now Prophecies are ceaſed; from whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that we may more eaſily fall into error concerning the true worſhip of God. Laſt of all, all men know, that the civil lawes of <hi>Moſes</hi> do not bind Chriſtians; of which ſort they are, which commanded a falſe Prophet, or an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate fallen to idolatry, to be deſtroyed. That truly theſe lawes, of which we now diſcourſe, do not oblige us, may eaſily be gathered from thence, That in all the New Teſtament there is no ſuch thing commanded, nor any where ſo much as lightly touched upon, that either A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates or Heretiques ought to be afflicted and brought to puniſhment by Chriſtians. Rightly hath <hi>Hierom</hi> declared in ſome part of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; <hi>I have learned by the Apoſtles appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to avoyd a man that is an Heretick, not to commit him to be burnt.</hi> For in this manner <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle adviſeth <hi>Titus: A man which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>is an heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, reject.</hi> And certainly he means ſuch an heretique, who is condemned by his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that he reſiſteth the manifeſt truth which he acknowledgeth; as may be diſcerned by his following words. How then ſhould Chriſtians be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119385:20"/> commanded to puniſh them, who were led into hereſie by deceitfull arguments, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they think invincible, and are affected with a ſimple ignorance of mind; or alſo being born of hereticall parents, ſucked their error together with their mothers milk. But ſo far is it from being true, that Chriſtians are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to trouble others for Religions ſake, that rather we are often warned it ſhall come to paſſe, that Chriſtians ſhall be troubled and brought to ſlaughter by other men, becauſe of their Religion. God in times paſt brought the Jews after ſuch a manner into the land of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, that after they had ſlain the worſhippers of falſe gods, they might poſſeſſe their country; promiſing them, if they ſhould obey his law, peace, wealth, victory over their enemies, and moreover ſuch ſtrength and ſuccours, that they might without any great difficulty ſuppreſſe Apoſtates, if any ſhould chance to ſpring up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. But we have learned of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that the condition of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhall be far otherwiſe: who were even <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 16</note> themſelves <hi>as ſheep in the midſt of wolves,</hi> and being grievouſly vexed and tormented, ſuffered a bloody death for the truths ſake: And they declared that we alſo ſhould be like <hi>ſheep ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the ſlaughter;</hi> And affirmed, that <hi>all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 36</note> 
               <hi>thoſe which will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> For ſuch is the nature of the <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 3. 12.</note> Chriſtian religion, that not many mighty men and of noble birth imbrace it; even as S. <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119385:21"/> teacheth, <hi>God hath choſen the weak and baſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>things of the world, and things which are deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and things which are not.</hi> How then could God enjoyne Chriſtians to kill Apoſtates, that is, thoſe which ſhould revolt from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to a Jewiſh or heatheniſh religion, and go over from men of low degree to Nobles, from weak to mighty men, and to their kind of holy worſhip. But if ſo be they are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to deſtroy them which altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Chriſtian religion, much leſſe Hereticks, who notwithſtanding acknowledge the majeſty and religious worſhip of Chriſt, although they do not ſufficiently underſtand it.</p>
            <p>Many alſo object that, If freedome of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be granted Heretiques, then hereſies will grow and increaſe. Yea verily they will more increaſe, if thou ſtrive to root them ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by force, eſpecially if the minds of men be otherwiſe bent to religion, honeſty and vertue. Thus much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience it ſelf hath taught us in theſe ages. The Proteſtant religion then increaſed moſt in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> when perſecution was oppoſed againſt it. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhewes as much: for they which endeavour to ſuppreſſe another mans religion by force, in ſo doing make their cauſe or religion to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and certainly leſſen the credit and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their own religion; but cauſe that to be well approved of, which they go about to ruine: for when they enter upon violent courſes, they ſeem to demonſtrate that they diſtruſt their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119385:21"/> cauſe, and deſpaire of victory, if the matter ſhould be debated by argumentation, therefore being deſtitute of reaſons, betake themſelves to force, and fly to carnall weapons, becauſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall are wanting, to bring mens minds under ſubjection: by which it comes to paſſe, that they purchaſe an opinion and report of cruelty to themſelves, and inflame other mens minds with hatred. They on the contrary, which are troubled for Religion ſake, eaſily get mens good will and affection. But whither mens favour and affection, thither alſo for the moſt part doth their faith incline. I will not alledge that now, That when the grievouſnes of puniſhment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt offenders is expoſed to the view, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people are not ſeldome moved to compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; moſt men not ſo much regarding and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to heart the deed, which either they never ſaw, or do no longer ſee; as the terribleneſſe of the puniſhment, which is ſubject to the ſight.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we think will come to paſſe, if they be deemed innocent, which ſuffer cruell puniſhments; if their life and manners be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of; if nothing be accuſed in them, but meer error of judgement? What if that alſo happen, that the people obſerve ſome blemiſh in their courſe of life, which trouble them, which they do not ſee in them ſo afflicted by themſelves? It is certain, that thoſe which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Religion ſake, how erroneous ſoever it be, do ſhew, that they eſteem all things leſſe than God, piety, and their own conſcience and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119385:22"/> ſalvation: which is only the part of good men, and ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are very great lovers of vertue, and fear God very much. It cannot happen other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then, but that they ſhould gain favour to themſelves, and beliefe and authority to that Religion which they ſo ſtoutly maintain, For this is the genius and proper quality of vertue, to purchaſe undoubted credit to it ſelf, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in matters belonging to Religion: Firſt, becauſe (as I have ſaid) mens favour fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vertue; and belief of what is ſaid, followes favour: And alſo, becauſe vertue is otherwiſe of it ſelf ſincere and undefiled, hating deceit, guile, and lying. But who may not rather believe him, and aſſent to his doctrine, in whom he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives to be moſt candor and ingenuity? Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it is no wayes credible, that God, who is ſo much delighted with vertue and piety, and ſo exceedingly rewards it, would deny the knowledge of true Religion to the better ſort of men, and grant it to the worſer. Laſt of all, The greater Vertue is not without juſt cauſe, thought to be the affection and proper quality even of the better Faith. Wherefore, as I have declared already, They, which by ſuffering any kind of cruelty and rigour for Religion ſake, ſhew forth moſt evident teſtimonies of their own vertue; eaſily incline and draw over people which love vertue, to their own ſide: They, on the contrary, which exerciſe cruelty againſt them, loſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the people, and diminiſh the credit of their Religion, which animates and ſtirs them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119385:22"/> up to ſo much cruelty againſt innocent and harmleſſe men. That I may be ſilent, that thoſe men themſelves which are afflicted for Religion ſake, by how much the more honeſt and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they be, are ſo much the more confirmed in their opinion, and the more vehemently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the love of their Religion, becauſe they think their own adverſaries judge it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controleable and invincible by ſtrength of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>From hence may eaſily be perceived what anſwer is to be made them which ſay, that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques are enemies to the Catholique Church and Religion, wherefore they ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the territories and limits of the Church, and Religion to be defended againſt them: That they are ravening Wolves, and therefore to be driven away from the Flock: That they give the ſons of God poyſon to drink, and ſo deſtroy their ſoules, and therefore ought not to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to have converſation with them: and that they ſell, and put by force upon the weak and ignorant Infants of Chriſt (of which there muſt alwaies be a great number) that poyſon, in ſtead of the ſaving drink of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>But be it ſo, that they be enemies to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion and Church; yet ſeeing they do not invade, nor intend to invade it with ſwords nor corporall weapons, they wage only a ſpirituall war with it: wherefore in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they are not to be vanquiſhed with carnall, but ſpirituall weapons, and to be driven either
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119385:23"/> from the Church, or brought into obedience thereof, by thoſe weapons (I ſay) wherewith the Apoſtles of old ſubdued the enemies of truth, overthrew the ſtrong holds of errors, and brought the world in ſubjection under Chriſt. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 3, 4.</note> For ſo ſaith <hi>Paul: For though we walk in the fleſh, we do not war after the fleſh: for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of our warfare are not carnall, but mighty through God to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringeth into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> But if thou wouldeſt drive Heretiques by carnall weapons out of the Church; thou wilt not deſtroy ſuch enemies, but exaſperate and provoke them, thou ſhalt not leſſen, but increaſe their number; and though thou mighteſt at length utterly root them out by this means, yet thou ſhalt not hereby defend thy Religion, but pollute and defile it. Long ſince did <hi>Lactantius</hi> give a right anſwer to the Gentiles, who thought that thoſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſes which they publikely perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, were to be defended by violence: Religion is to be defended, quoth he, not by killing, but by dying; not by cruelty, but by patience. And a little after, <hi>If thou wouldſt defend Religion with blood, with torments, with miſchief, then it will not be defended, but defiled and corrupted; For nothing is ſo free and voluntary as Religion,</hi> and ſo onwards. Truly Chriſtian Religion is not better known by urging and preſſing the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119385:23"/> truth, than by inculcating and exhorting men to charity, peace, meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe, and patience. It will have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors thereof to overcome their enemies, and not to be overcome by them, with theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. It doth not ſo defend the truth of matters belonging to Religion, as that it would have them break the bonds of humane and civil ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety for that purpoſe, which propagate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it: but rather it more ſtrictly obligeth them to obſerve thoſe duties, and to make good the law of charity towards all men, and to love the bonds of peace. Therefore if thou ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to maintaine the Chriſtian religion by force, if by mirchief, if by puniſhments; even by ſo doing thou wilt moſt of all offend againſt it. Let the ſame anſwer ſuffice them who ſtick not to affirme, that Heretiques are ravening wolves, and ought to be driven out of the flock. Let them be driven out indeed with the Crook of the Paſtors of the Church, but not with a wooden or iron one, but with one which is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and proper to the Eccleſiaſticall function. Heretiques do not teare the ſheep with their nailes, nor bite them with their teeth: but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hurt the flock with Reaſons and Arguments, which in the judgement of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, are deceitfull: Let theſe therefore be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted and beaten off with ſtronger reaſons, and let the ſheep be admoniſhed to beware and take heed to themſelves that they be not enſnared by them, as Chriſt did, and after him the Apoſtles.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119385:24"/> By this means the flock of Chriſt will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently armed againſt their violence; unleſſe thou wouldeſt ſay, that the ſheep were not ſufficiently armed againſt the violence &amp; incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of wolves, by Chriſt the great ſhepherd of of the ſheep, and by his Apoſtles their moſt faithfull keepers, becauſe that they neither uſed force themſelves, nor adviſed others to do it. Moreover, if thou makeſt uſe of externall force, thou wilt not thereby root out thoſe ſcruples and doubts, which Heretiques perhaps have ſowed in the minds of believers, but wilt adde ſtrength to them: Neither wilt thou hinder them from being wolves, but cauſe them to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from profeſsing and detecting themſelves to be ſuch, whilſt they in the mean while cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves with ſheep skins, may remain without any danger of puniſhment preſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the flock. But if thou uſeſt Arguments only, and Eccleſiaſticall cenſures, thou wilt drive the wolves from the flock; For if any ſhall be more wicked than others, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding whatſoever hath been ſaid in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of their errors, will ſtill be in love with them; when no feare of puniſhment hinders them, will ſhew themſelves in publike, and after open cenſure and rebuke, will be excluded the eccleſiaſticall ſheepfold, neither ſhall have cauſe to charge any one as guilty of their duſtruction, beſides themſelves and their own ſtubborneſſe. Their blood will be upon their own heads, as the holy Scripture ſpeaketh, Their deſtruction
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119385:24"/> ſhall not be imputed to their Paſtors, becauſe they admoniſhed them, they armed them againſt errors, and endeavoured as much as in them lay to keep them in the path that leadeth to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore, as the Prophet ſaith, thoſe <hi>wicked ones ſhall die in their iniquity,</hi> but the paſtors have delivered their ſoule. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſttnding the Church will reap the benefit, for which alſo God ſuffers hereſies ſometimes to ſpring up among the faithfull, as <hi>Paul</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that they which are <hi>approved, may be made manifeſt among them.</hi> Which benefit doth not follow, if hereticks be violently ſuppreſſed; for by ſuch dealing, even the wicked, repreſſed by feare, will labour to carry the outward guize of believers, as much as honeſt men, ſo that there may appeare no difference between them: yea, a heretick, who ſhall dare to riſe up againſt an armed religion, and to profeſſe and defend hereſie with the danger of his eſtate, or of life it ſelf; will ſhew forth a greater proofe of vertue, than he which, guarded with power, oppoſeth a hereſie, or at leaſt defendeth a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which is attended with force and power: For neither can it then appear whether he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in his true opinion, or defends it for the goodneſſe of his cauſe, or to confirm his own power, or for feare of another mans power. But on the contrary, he which dares oppoſe himſelf againſt a Religion which is armed with power, or revolt from it, and contemn all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers for Religion ſake, doth demonſtrate (as I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119385:25"/> have ſaid before) that he lightly eſteems all things in compariſon of God, piety, conſcience, and eternall ſalvation. By this time, that alſo is evident enough, that the minds of believers, and of Chriſts little ones, may be ſo prepared and guarded by the care and diligence of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, eſpecially ſeeing there be ſo many, not only thouſands, but even millions of them; that the poyſon which heretiques adminiſter unto ſuch, cannot hurt them, although no violence be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed againſt heretiques. Neither verily may it be imagined, that Heretiques arguments are ſo plauſible, that they may withdraw the more ſimple and ignorant ſort of men from the ſaving truth, which are lovers of truth, and earneſtly deſire their own ſalvation; although the Truth, well expounded, and armed with ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, be oppoſed with thoſe Reaſons. For truth, eſpecially heavenly and ſaving truth, is of ſuch a nature, that it ſinks more eaſily into a mind that is diſpoſed to vertue, if it be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely propounded, and confirmed beſides with ſolid arguments, than falſhood and error: She hath a certain wonderfull clearneſſe and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her own, by which ſhe dazles and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes their minds, which do not purpoſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take knowledge of her; neither is ſhe more approved of by ſubtile, than by ſimple ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, which are endued but with common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſenſe and apprehenſion. <hi>I thank thee</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>O Father, Lord of heaven and earth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119385:25"/> 
               <hi>and prudent, and haſt revealed them to babes:</hi> And S. Paul: <hi>God hath choſen the fooliſh things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor: 1. 27.</note> 
               <hi>of the world to confound the wiſe.</hi> Therefore as yet no cauſe appeares, why we ſhould think that a remedy againſt the poyſon of hereſie, is placed in violence and arms: but rather it appeares that there is need of ſome other wholſome anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote againſt the venome of Errors.</p>
            <p>Perhaps ſome man may ſtill object, that to grant Heretiques liberty of Religion, muſt needs wound and trouble the conſcience of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, becauſe if liberty of Religion be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them, the Commonwealth will be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into factions, and a way laid open for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, tumults, and inteſtine garboiles and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: For the minds of the people are knit and united together by conſent in Religion; but by difference and diſagreement therein they are divided and diſtracted; neither can it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe happen, but that they who are zealouſly affected to Religion, ſhould riſe up in arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, at ſome time or other, whom they are fully perſwaded do ſpread abroad ungodly and peſtilent doctrine. Neither truly the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of Magiſtrates and Catholique Paſtors doth permit them to quench the zeale and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the people to the Catholique religion, which they ought rather to cheriſh and increaſe. Therefore they cannot ſo bridle and repreſſe the fury of the people which are inflamed with a deadly hatred againſt Heretiques, but that it will at ſome time or other break forth in violence
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119385:26"/> againſt Heretiques. Yet notwithſtanding in the mean while it is the duty of the Magiſtrate to preſerve ſafe and ſound the publike peace, to hinder tumults, to take out of the way what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may occaſion them. If he doth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, he offends his own conſcience, and doth not execute that office which God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his charge. Wherefore when as he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot, or ought not to ſuppreſſe the people fervently affected to Religion, from riſing up in violence againſt Heretiques; there remains one courſe only to be taken, which is, to expell He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, and to ſuffer and eſtabliſh but one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in one Country, and that to be the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique religion. Theſe ſayings may ſeem to ſome man very plauſible, yet if thou diligently obſerve, thou ſhalt find them to be ſuch, which even experience it ſelf doth very much confute: for ſo far is it from being true, that this is the way, and the only way, to free a Commonwealth from tumults and ſeditions, that none is more apt and commodious to raiſe them up; And it is a wonder to me that wiſe men have not yet learned ſo much, or rather would not learn by experience, which is ſaid to be the ſchool-miſtris even of fooles. If ancient examples be not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull enough to perſwade thee, yet look upon thoſe which are modern and of latter times, and almoſt ſubject to thy view: Behold <hi>France,</hi> oftentimes ſwimming with the blood of its own inhabitants, by reaſon of thoſe wars which were raiſed for Religion, which could never be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119385:26"/> ended till liberty of Religion was granted He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques. Look upon the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and a war laſting ſo many yeares, which is both la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, and famous, for as many great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes of the Catholiques, as of Heretiques. Behold <hi>Germany,</hi> or rather the ſepulchre of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> which even to this day is miſerably trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a moſt cruell war. I ſhall think him blinde, who doth not ſee, that by oppoſing He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques with force, tumults and wars are raiſed up, not quelled and prevented; But I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be an iron-hearted man, who is not troubled and grieved for ſuch tragicall and ſad examples. It were truly to be wiſhed, that there were but one Religion in a Kingdome, and that the true one; for neither is it a queſtion, but that by this meanes the minds of men may be more united together in mutuall good will and affection: Yet thus much we deny, that by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Religions the minds of the people are altogether ſo diſtracted and divided, that a civill concord and a mutuall good will between Inhabitants of the ſame city or kingdom, cannot ſtand together with that difference in Religion. Moreover, if they which beare rule in any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Kingdome, would but prevaile a little with their affections to tolerate Heretiques which are weak, they will knit rather and binde the minds of Heretiques in good will toward them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; For that which they in juſtice do, that, Heretiques which are weaker in ſtrength, will account a courteſie, and aſcribe it to their gentle
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119385:27"/> diſpoſition, bounty and benevolence. Wherefore they which deny that peace can remain in a Commonwealth, if there be diverſity of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it; They alſo muſt deny, that a weaker party, which is of a different Religion, may be tolerated by the ſtronger in a Kingdome: which whoſoever ſhall affirm, they alſo ſhall excuſe the Heathens, who in former Ages would not tolerate Chriſtians that were weaker than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe indeed they could not. As much is to be aſſerted and avouched concerning <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochus</hi> and other Kings, who in former times grievouſly afflicted the Jewes, over whom they had dominion, for Religion ſake. But why ſhould that be denied to be feaſible, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to have been often done, as we ſee it now adayes to be under the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits Chriſtians in ſeverall parts of his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to exerciſe their own Religion. Why do ſo many endeavour, and ſome by writing books, others by word of mouth, to perſwade the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates not to grant a Toleration unto Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, which are not ſo ſtrong as themſelves in power? But why do they feare leſt that be granted, which cannot be? But perhaps they which think it cannot be admitted, judge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men according to their own diſpoſition, and are led either with an over-hot and prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous zeale, or ſo enraged and tranſported with the wilfulneſſe and unrulineſſe of their own mind, and confidence of their own ſtrength, that they think thoſe which are not ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119385:27"/> as themſelves, may not be endured; whom I believe they would permit, if they were more powerfull. A civill peace therefore may (as I have ſaid) conſiſt even where there is difference of opinion in matters belonging to Religion. That is a known and a uſuall proverb among the common people: <hi>Good men may differ in opinion even about the ſame matters, without any breach of friendſhip.</hi> To which ſenſe that alſo tends, which is as common: <hi>A friend to the perſon, yet an enemy to the cauſe.</hi> Neither doth it leſſe concern matters of Religion, than State-affaires. Moreover, if the nature of the matter be conſidered; diſagreement in State-affaires is more hurtfull to a Civill peace and concord, than difference in opinions about a matter of Piety, which (if men would moderate and bridle their affections, eſpecially thoſe which are moſt powerfull) leaves the bond of concord ſafe and ſecure in a Commonwealth, even for becauſe it doth not of it ſelf concern Civil ſociety. So in former ages, Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours which imbraced the Chriſtian religion, enjoyed a quiet dominion, although they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Pagans, which oppoſed it. But heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Emperors, which tolerated Chriſtians, had a far more peaceable reigne: Verily Chriſtians were no hinderance to the continuance of peace in the Commonwealth, although they did boldly and ingeniouſly profeſſe their Religion, and did much abhorre that Heatheniſh impiety which was then publikely exerciſed; and teſtified that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119385:28"/> they had rather die a thouſand deaths, than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and approve of it. Alſo ſome Chriſtian Emperours tolerated Heretiques, ſuch as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> were, and that at <hi>Rome</hi> too, without any diſturbance of the publike peace. So alſo <hi>Germany</hi> remained quiet a long time, in diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Religions, and had continued ſo even till this time, unleſſe either ſome very raſh or am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Counſels had at length prevailed. That the like is to be judged of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> they will eaſily perceive, who are not ignorant of the paſſages there.</p>
            <p>But as for that which ſome men plead, that the zeal of Catholike religion ought not to be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but even cheriſhed and fomented: which ſometimes doth ſo incenſe the people, that they are led thereby to invade, plunder, and demoliſh Heretiques churches, oratories, and houſes. Verily they ſhew themſelves to be unacquainted with the affairs of the world, and to be not only very little mindfull of Chriſt, but alſo of civil lawes: For is this a zeale beſeeming Chriſtians, to invade other mens properties by force? to ruinate and pull down other mens churches, by tumult, by ſedition, without any command from the Magiſtrate, before any lawful judgment hath paſſed, and of their own accord and pleaſure to ruine and deſtroy other men? Then Chriſt wanted zeale; then the Apoſtles wanted zeal; then all Chriſtians which lived ſince them, wanted zeale, who never did, nor purpoſed to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119385:28"/> do any ſuch things: They ſuffered indeed many ſuch things, but they never did the like to others. That is not the zeal of Religion, but the rage and fury of the people, often ſtirred up with hope of prey: Vnleſſe perhaps thou mayeſt call it that, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>is not according to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 2</note> 
               <hi>knowledge,</hi> and as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh, is <hi>bitter:</hi> for this, as he ſheweth, raiſeth tumults, and <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 14, 16.</note> every evill work. That zeale which is joyned with wiſdome and knowledge, is of another nature; for that wiſdome doth not ſuffer zeale to grow to ſeditions and tumults, but it is moſt deſirous of peace and quietneſſe: whereof the ſame Apoſtle ſaith a little after, <hi>The wiſdome that is from above is peaceable, gentle, and eaſie</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ver. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits.</hi> Wherefore it is ſo far from being true, That, that Zeal which breaketh forth into tumults, rapines, burnings with fire, ſtripes and ſlaughters; is to be nouriſhed and fomented by the Paſtors of Chriſtian people: That rather it is by all means poſſible to be ſuppreſſed, and brought within the bounds of modeſty, meekneſſe, and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; leſt they which ſhould be the heralds and meſſengers of peace, become trumpets of ſedition, and incenſers of the publike calamity and ruine. So far alſo is it from being true, that the Magiſtrate ought to cheriſh this licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the people, that he ought rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain it upon all occaſions, if ſo be he would provide for the good of Religion, which deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſuch ſinfull deeds; and for the tranquility of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119385:29"/> the Commonwealth; and alſo diſcharge that office which is committed to him by God, and ſatisfie his own conſcience. For nothing is more deſtructive to a Commonwealth, than to ſuffer the liberty, reputation, goods, or life, even of a wicked man, to be obnoxious to the luſt of a tumultuous people. Therefore although Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques were at length to be reſtrained by force, yet nevertheleſſe that were not to be executed by the tumult and ſedition of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but in a ſetled and lawfull way of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Magiſtrate. Wiſe Magiſtrates and good Princes alwayes take order, that offenders be not expoſed to the licenciouſneſſe of the people, which neither knows how to obſerve a juſt meaſure in puniſhment, neither is more cruell to evill and guilty, than good and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent men, and never makes a ſtand where it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, but oftentimes creepeth on farther. But if then Heretiques are not to be expoſed to the zeal or fury of the common People, although they were at length to be puniſhed: how much leſſe ought that to be permitted, if they are not to be puniſhed with Civil puniſhments.</p>
            <p>Thus much I thinke fit to ſay yet, before I leave this point or argument; that thoſe which judge it not expedient to tollerate Heretiques, becauſe they diſturb the Peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth by their difference in religion, do uſe the ſame argument, which Infidels or Heretiques may eaſily retort upon them in their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. Truly <hi>Haman</hi> uſed the like argument
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119385:29"/> in former times, that he might ſhew that the Jews were to be rooted out, charging them alſo with Treaſon, as that they contemned the Kings commands: which malicious accuſation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from no other ground, then becauſe the Iews would not obey in any wiſe the Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees in matters belonging to Religion: to which calumny they are alwayes obnoxious, which follow a different religion from that which the ſupreame Magiſtrate approves of, and defends by force. For ſo it is written in the Letters, which that <hi>Haman</hi> publiſhed in the name of the King: <hi>Haman</hi> declared unto us, that in all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <note place="margin">Heſt. 13. 4</note> throughout the world there was ſcattered a certain People, that had Laws contrary to all Nations, and continually deſpiſed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of Kings, ſo as the uniting of our Kingdomes cannot go forward. Seeing then we underſtand that this People alone is continually in oppoſition unto all men, differing in the ſtrange manner of their Laws, and evill affected to our State, working all the miſchief they can, that our Kingdome may not be firmly eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Therefore have wee commanded that all they that are ſignified in writing unto you by <hi>Haman</hi> (who is ordained over the affairs, and is next unto us) ſhall all, with their wives and children be utterly deſtroyed by the ſword of their enemies. Neither skils it any thing in this caſe, that theſe are Believers, thoſe Infidels; theſe Catholiques, thoſe Heretiques. For if diverſity of religion diſturbes the peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119385:30"/> the Catholique religion will as much trouble it in a Hereticall Common-wealth, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially allowing of the ſlaughter of Heretiques, as an Hereticall religion in a Catholique: Yea, a Hereticall religion which diſallows of any ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or proſecuting of Heretiques, will far leſſe cauſe it, than the Catholique religion. And moreover every man thinks that he hath a right opinion and beliefe concerning religion; and a Catholique is as much a Heretique in the eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Heretique, as a Heretique is in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Catholique. Therefore if that reaſon be true, which I confute, an hereticall Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot but think that his courſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the peace of his Kingdome, muſt be to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Catholiques out of the bounds thereof. But if Catholiques like not this, neither let them think it fit for themſelves, to expell Heretiques their Common-wealths.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119385:30"/>
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Catholiques ought to grant Heretiques Liberty of Religion, and to provide for their Security.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>VVEE have ſhewed in the foregoing Chapter, that the liberty of Religion, which Heretiques deſire, requires nothing elſe, but that they may receive no hurt, nor be affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with any puniſhment for Hereſie: in one word, that a Civill peace may be accepted of with them. But now the firſt argument wee bring to prove that Catholiques ought to live peaceably with them, is, becauſe they may do it with a ſafe conſcience, as hath been hitherto ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne. But if Catholiques may with a ſafe conſcience live peaceably with them, then they are bound to do ſo. For thus ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 18. Heb. 12. 14.</note> 
               <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as in you is, have peace with all men.</hi> And in another place: <hi>Follow peace with all men.</hi> But yet both nature and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon beſides declare, that any man ought to live peaceably with all thoſe, with whom he may; eſpecially with ſuch as earneſtly deſire, and importunately ask it. But if Heathens alſo thought it good to purchaſe peace oftentimes even upon harſh and unjuſt termes, how much more are Chriſtians bound to accept of a juſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119385:31"/> peace offered them by others, even of their own accord, or grant it them at their requeſt? <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Peacemakers,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>for they ſhall be called the children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if Catholiques ſhould deny Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques liberty or peace, and ſhould hold it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to puniſh them, and ſo ſhould puniſh them for profeſſing that religion which differs from the Cathoique, they would force them, as much as in them lyed to their own religion. But no man ought to be forced, or compelled by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward violence to the Chriſtian religion. Firſt, becauſe the diſpoſition and nature of religion, eſpecially ſpirituall, and perfect religion, ſuch as is the Chriſtian religion, is repugnant to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion. Rightly ſaith <hi>Lactantius,</hi> Religion cannot be compelled: And again, nothing is ſo voluntary as Religion, which if the minde of him that ſacrificeth diſlike, then it is taken away, then it becomes none at all. And therefore <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſaith, It is not the property of religion to force religion, which ought to be freely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, not by force. And then becauſe by this meanes many are conſtrained to counterfeit and fain religion; for that violence cannot cauſe a man to think otherwiſe then he doth. An opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion can neither be thurſt into the minde by vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, nor extorted and wreſted from it. That is all force can do, to cauſe a man to approve of that opinion in words, which he diſlikes in his heart. But ſuch a ſimulation and hypocriſie is abominable to God, and ought to be alſo to all
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119385:31"/> men; and it is hurtfull both to the Church, and to hypocrites themſelves. To the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe hypocrites are ſecret enemies, whom the Church foſters in her boſome as Serpents: For they cannot but hate that Church, by which they believe themſelves to be moſt unjuſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and deſire, and if they can, work the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſtruction thereof. It is hurtfull to hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites themſelves, becauſe it brings them to eternall deſtruction. Our Saviour ſaith of that evill ſervant, <hi>That the Lord ſhall appoint him his portion with the hypocrites, there ſhall be weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> And truly this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment would befall them, although they ſhould think that this ſimulation and diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were lawfull; but whoſoever amongſt them are more ſincere and vertuous then others; in doing ſo wound their conſcience moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly, and ſo ſin moſt hainouſly againſt God, becauſe they Profeſſe that religion which they hate and abhor in their minde, and performe thoſe religious exerciſes, which they condemne, and believe to be diſpleaſing to God. But he ſins moſt hainouſly, which violates his conſcience. If he ſins, and therefore is damned, who doth a thing which is otherwiſe lawfull in it ſelfe, with a doubting conſcience, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, he ſins far more hainouſly, and more juſtly is <note place="margin">Rom 14. 23.</note> condemned who doth any thing directly againſt his conſcience, and the judgement of his own minde. Hence it is that Divines ſay (they are the words of a moſt famous man amongſt the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119385:32"/> Catholique doctors) that the conſcience, though it be erroneous binds, ſo that it is never lawfull to do any thing againſt it, but it behoveth a man to lay it aſide, and diſcharge himſelfe of it by the prudent counſell of reaſon, and of wiſe men; or if he cannot do that, he is bound to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, to wit, if his reſolution, and the matter in hand may not be deferred. Wherefore they which force others to deſert their own religion and embrace the Catholique againſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, compell them, as much as in them is, to ſin moſt grievouſly. But how may he be judged free from ſinning greatly, who forceth other men to ſin greatly.</p>
            <p>But ſome man may here object, (of which we ſpake alſo in the former Chapter) That God nevertheleſſe commanded them under the Law, to puniſh thoſe with death, which ſhould worſhip ſtrange and falſe gods. Wherefore at leaſt in ſuch a caſe, God would have men to be forced to the true Religion, neither would have any regard to be had of that point, That Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be free; and that many, by ſuch means as force, may be driven to ſimulation, or compelled to do any thing againſt conſcience. We might anſwer thus: That it is lawfull for God, who as he is Lord of all other things, ſo alſo of our conſciences, and of whoſe will and pleaſure the ſtate and way of Religion depends; To ſwerve from the ordinary path and method of things, and to ordain many things, which it is not lawfull for us to ordain or effect. But
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119385:32"/> we will not now make uſe of this anſwer. Thus much firſt we affirm; That even Catholique Doctors both ancient and modern, have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and any one that will ſeriouſly bend his mind to it will eaſily ſee, that the Jewiſh religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was carnall, and conſiſted moſt in externall matters; not ſpirituall and perfect, ſuch as we have ſaid the Chriſtian to be: wherefore it is no wonder that God would force men in ſome reſpects by carnall puniſhments, to a carnall religion; and that the genius and proper quality of Religion, which is, that it be free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, did not ſhew forth it ſelf in every point in that Religion. But the proper quality of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and perfect Religion, is of another tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which requires moſt of all the Minde of man: wherefore God would not have it eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by externall force, nor by terror of Civil, but Eternal puniſhments: &amp; a great deal rather would have it imprinted and ingrafted in the minds of men by the love of moſt holy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And in the next place it is to be noted, that the Jewiſh religion was both ſo ordained and ſetled from the beginning, and afterwards continued and adminiſtred; that it may juſtly be affirmed, that violence was no more offered to the conſciences of the Jews, when they were deterred by threatning puniſhments from wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping ſtrange gods, and from contempt of the Law, than it is to their conſciences, who, if they be Inhabitants of any Kingdome, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred by threatning puniſhments from yielding
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119385:33"/> that honour which is due unto a King, to any beſides their own King; or from the contempt and breach of thoſe Lawes which are enacted and eſtabliſhed by a lawfull power, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand no diſhoneſt matter. For God appearing openly from the very beginning in the mountain Sinai, ſo ſhewed himſelf to be the only God, in the ſight of all the people, and publiſhed his Law unto them, that no man could doubt but that he was both their only God, and ſo to be worſhipped only as a God, and that the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> came from him. From whence it came to paſſe, that all the people, none making any oppoſition at all, made a covenant with God by <hi>Moſes</hi> concerning that Law. And then after the Law was now eſtabliſhed, God both promiſed that he would ever and anon raiſe up Prophets to the people of Iſrael from amongſt themſelves, by whom the Jewes might ask his advice, and find out his minde, not only concerning matters pertaining to Religion, but even ſuch as belong to the Commonwealth, yea and ſuch as concern houſhold affairs: And really alſo performed it, and had ſtill a great deal more performed it, if the people had remained conſtant in obſerving the Law. Beſides other propheſies and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnings, God ordained an ordinary way of asking his counſel by the Prieſts <hi>Ephod,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi> as the holy Scripture cals it. And he moreover revealed ſecret and hidden matters to ſuch as ſought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut his will by lot, and ſhewed what they were to do: and as often as
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119385:33"/> the people followed Gods counſel, all things ſucceeded proſperouſly with them; ſo that the event it ſelf declared, thoſe anſwers came from God. Therefore the ſtate of things was in a manner, as if God had been a certain King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people of Iſrael, even in civil and earthly matters, dwelling in the Tabernacle as in a certain Kingly palace, and abiding in the Ark, and from thence informing the people of his will by the Prieſts, or other Prophets, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that were to wait near his perſon. He gave anſwers about undertaking and waging of war, about chooſing of Captains and Commanders, and other ſuch like matters: He very often ſhewed wonders, to declare that himſelf dwelt in the midſt of that people. Wherefore things were then ſo ordered, as if ſome King contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf within his own palace, neither ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering himſelf to be ſeen of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were approached unto only by his Nobles, gave anſwers by them to the reſt, and publiſhed ſtatutes, and ruled the common-wealth accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own will and pleaſure; and ſo would have a Kingly honour to be attributed to none beſides himſelf, and would have his Lawes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding no diſhoneſt thing (as I have ſaid) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht with a threatning of puniſhment, to be obeyed by all his ſubjects. By taking which courſe, he were to be thought to do no proper violence to mens conſciences, or to force them to ſimulation, but to hinder and repreſſe only the obſtinacie and rebellion of his own ſubjects.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119385:34"/> But the diſpoſition of Religion is far otherwiſe now after that God would be ſought to no longer upon earth, but in heaven, and took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thoſe manifeſt ſignes of his preſence, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth uphold and preſerve the Religion which he hath ordained after ſuch a conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and open manner; doth not ſtir up Prophets, doth no longer give anſwers, but acts and orders all things more ſecretly, for ſo much the greater triall of mens faith: For as the caſe now is, men fall more eaſily into error, and violence is offered to the conſcience, if thou ſhalt make any one quit his error by threatning of puniſhments, and force him to a truth which is not demonſtrated by ſuch clear teſtimonies: And from thence alſo follows this concluſion, That they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a ſimulation, which is hatefull to God, who being not convinced by arguments and reaſons, are compelled by force to imbrace a Religion, how true ſoever it be: In which point truly they have hitherto ſo erred, who thought it meet for Heretiques to be ſuppreſſed by violence; that taking a middle courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Legal ſeverity, and a Chriſtian gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they obtained the end of neither of them: For God in former times would not have Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and worſhippers of falſe gods, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of his Law, to be ſpared, but command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to be ſlain without mercy; for he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not this puniſhment as a remedy againſt their error, but as a revengement againſt their unpardonable wickedneſſe and contumacie. But
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119385:34"/> thoſe which hold it requiſite for Heretiques to be violently dealt withall, becauſe they plainly ſee that many of them do not ſin through ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſſe, but are led away by error, thoſe they think fit to be ſpared; but upon ſuch a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they recall their error; although they ſee that they would never have recalled it, unleſſe they had been driven to it by terror of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore that they rather pretend the Catholique religion, than approve of it. Therefore they do not deſtroy thoſe which have an evill opinion concerning God and matters belonging to Religion, but only hinder them from profeſſing it outwardly, which the Law never intended. But whilſt they puniſh thoſe, or deprive tham even of life, which dare not for fear of conſcience renounce their error, they neither perform the duty of Chriſtian meeknes, nor obtain the end thereof, which is that erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous perſons may be brought into the way, and be reſtored. And that I may utter the whole matter in a word; by doing thus, they tolerate the worſer ſort, and deſtroy the better: for they are better and more vertuous, who, when they are not convinced of an error, will not renounce it, for fear of wounding their conſcience, and of offending againſt God; than thoſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn in words againſt their conſcience, an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, though in it ſelf erroneous, yet that which they believe to be true, and agreeable to the word of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus declared, we will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119385:35"/> adde yet ſome other arguments, by which we may ſhew, that Catholiques ought to live quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with Heretiques, and not to ſuppreſſe them by force. I will not now make mention of thoſe ſeditions, wars and tumults, which might eaſily proceed from denying Liberty of Religion to Heretiques, eſpecially in a Nation that is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to liberty, that is unapt to ſuffer any yoke or ſervitude, much more that, than which none is more grievous, even that by which mens conſciences are oppreſſed. We ſhewed the truth of this matter by moſt evident examples in the former Chapter, which without our informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any man may ſee. Neither verily is it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that Heretiques themſelves raiſe tumults, even though Heretiques be ſuppreſſed; A ſparkle of diſcord may take hold on Catholiques them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, partly by the obligations of kindred, and laws of frieneſhip and alliance, by which they are knit and allied to Heretiques; partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe examples ſhewed upon Heretiques, would in a ſhort time creep further, For examples do not uſe to ſtop &amp; ceaſe where they firſt began, and ſo much the leſſe thoſe of which we treat, if any gain might accrue and riſe to others by the oppreſſion of Heretiques: what, ſhall we think that they will not find ſome ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, who covet other mens goods, to make thoſe heretiques, or abettors and followers of heretiques, whoſe riches they greedily gape af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; eſpecially if they ſhall perceive them to be obnoxious, and to lie open to injury? But what
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119385:35"/> ſhall I ſay of the authority and dominion of the Clergie over the Politick State? The matter may eaſily be diſcerned by the hiſtory of thoſe times, which were before the riſe of hereſies, How eaſily might a ſpeech more free than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, uttered againſt the Eccleſiaſticall State, be drawn into the crime of Hereſie? and that which was ſpoken againſt the behaviour or actions of Clergie-men, be wreſted to a contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely and reproach of Religion it ſelf? eſpecially when thou ſhouldeſt have both thine Accuſers and Judges out of the ſame ſtate and order of men. Might not even this very thing it ſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford occaſion to new motions and tumults? But let others look to this. We would in this place have that called to memory, which we ſpake of in the former chapter; That by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving Heretiques of Liberty in Religion, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies are not only not ſuppreſſed and rooted out, but even by how much the more honeſt the mindes of any people be, by ſo much the more they are increaſed: We adde now thus much: That by deniall thereof, Atheiſme ſprings up in many mens hearts, which is worſe than any kind of hereſie whatſoever. For, Conſcience is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and deſtroyed in thoſe men, in whom there is not ſo great honeſty, and ſo great vertue and power of conſcience as there ought to be, when they are troubled for Religion; and ſo hypocriſie, and counterfeiting of that Religion unto which they are forced, is begotten in them, and ſo atheiſme and profaneſſe, which hath no
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119385:36"/> ſavour at all of holines and religion, ſprings up. But as for thoſe men in whom there is a greater honeſty and integrity of minde, and a regard of conſcience, and a feare of God; in thoſe men the love of their Religion is inflamed and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by perſecution, as a fire is by caſting oyle into it: and it layes hold on (as I may ſo ſay) with an open and light fire whatſoever comes nigh it, and oftentimes creeps on further, for thoſe cauſes mentioned in the former chapter: concerning which point, <hi>Thuanus,</hi> a Catholique, wrote much (among other men) in the Preface which he ſet before his Hiſtories. But if thou ſayeſt, that a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition</hi> is ſomewhere uſed, yet Hereſies do not creep on farther there: I would have thee alſo to conſider, whether A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme doth not creep into the place of hereſie? Truly not a few even of the Catholiques com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of that matter, who are well acquainted with thoſe countries: Although beſides, many thouſands were found to be in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> but a few years ago, of thoſe, who either took unto themſelves the name, or had it given them by the people, of Illuminated perſons, and were accounted for heretiques. But what doſt thou think many foſter privily in their mind? Experience it ſelf doth ſufficiently declare, that in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> the Jewiſh and Saraceni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call religion could not for ſome ages be rooted out of mens minds by bringing in an Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>But verily although there were not ſo great inconveniencies, as I have recorded, yet there
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119385:36"/> would be others, which ought to diſſwade Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques from holding it fitting for Heretiques to be puniſhed. For even that one thing ought to prevaile with them, which we ſpake of in the former Chapter, that the ſafety of the Church, and of Religion doth no wayes require, that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques be ſet upon by violence, which alſo the Catholiques themſelves ſufficiently confirme, when they affirme that the Church is founded upon a Rock, ſo that it can neither by force, nor by guile be overthrowne, which Chriſt ſignified, when he ſaid, <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it.</hi> Neither truly is it agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that this ſtability, and immovable conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Church ſhould conſiſt in that, that ſhe ſhall prevaile by Armes and civill power over her enemies: for becauſe that then the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rather appeared, when that ſo godly a build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was brought from its firſt foundations to full perfection. The Catholiques themſelves ſhew another kinde of ſupportance for it, that Spirit of truth which is alwayes preſent with the Church, which alwayes upholds it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves it ſafe from all ruine. But ſhall we think that that Spirit of truth, which in former Ages erected the holy building of the Church, maugre all the oppoſition of Satan, and the whole world, and brought it to ſuch a greatneſſe by impotent and unarmed men, and defended it againſt arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed errour and impiety, is become now adayes ſo weak and feeble, that he can no longer main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his own work without ſtrength of Arms:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119385:37"/> and that he ſtands in need of that power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend religion and the Church, which he before ſubdued, otherwiſe without its help, the Church muſt needs fall to ruine? But if the ſafety of the Church, and of the Catholique religion doth not require that Heretiques be overwhelmed by force, why doe the Catholiques hold it fit for them to be born down with violence? For who can think, eſpecially that is a Chriſtian, that uſe is to be made of violence, puniſhments and arms, without neceſſity? For it is the property of gentleneſſe to ſpare, where thou mayeſt ſpare; eſpecially where ſo many thouſands of men were to be dragged and haul'd to puniſhment, ſo many ſoules to be deſtroyed. Furthermore, the hope of that great benefit which may proceeds from toleration of Heretiques, ought to incline the Catholiques to more gentle reſolutions. For by ſuch a toleration they would purchaſe the praiſe to themſelves of meekneſſe, equity, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, and moderation, and would gaine their good wils and affections, which being once gained, it is an eaſie matter to perſwade them of the truth which is founded upon ſolid argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Moreover, when Heretiques are ſo born withall, they have a time to recollect and amend themſelves, and thoſe errours which at the firſt view ſeemed plauſible, after their paint and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour is by little and little diſcovered; begin to leſſe delight men, and at length decay: but truth it ſelf is ſtrengthened by delay: and being after a manner daſh: againſt falſhood and untruth, by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119385:37"/> its own vertue and ſtrength breaks it in pieces, and the brightneſſe of it by this colliſion ſhines forth more clearly. Wherefore, when as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect hereof there is no neceſſity of troubling Heretiques, and of provoking them with the terribleneſſe of puniſhments, but hence from le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and gentleneſſe there is hope of exceeding fruit and benefit belonging to the everlaſting ſalvation of ſo many thouſands, yea millions; What Chriſtian man will be of ſo rigorous and cruell a diſpoſition, that he can hold it fit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe cruelty, rather then patience and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards thoſe men? Catholiques ought to be led and moved alſo in this point by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of God himſelf, whoſe children we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelves to be; and of Chriſt the Saviour of the whole world, who was wont to uſe very great lenity and gentleneſſe towards erroneous perſons. God in former times declared in his Law, which in other matters was ſevere, <hi>That all the people of Iſrael, and ſtrangers, which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed amongst them ſhould be forgiven if they committed any thing through ignorance;</hi> And truly, for this very reaſon, becauſe they did it through ignorance or errour, not through pride, and ſtubbornneſſe of heart. But what ſhall wee ſay of Chriſt, who came into the world for that purpoſe, <hi>That he might ſave ſinners? Paul</hi> writes of himſelf, that Chriſt Ieſus our Lord put him in his ſervice, who was before a <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, and a Perſecutor,</hi> and an <hi>Oppreſſour:</hi> but, ſaith he, <hi>I was received to mercy, becauſe I</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119385:38"/> 
               <hi>did it ignorantly, through unbeliefe.</hi> Behold, he obtained pardon for ſo great ſins as blaſphemy, perſecution, reproaches and oppreſſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he troubled and afflicted the godly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did thoſe things ignorantly, through unbeliefe, and that at ſuch a time, wherein the memory was yet freſh of thoſe great miracles, and infinite in number, which were wrought by Chriſt; when thoſe wonderfull deeds of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were daily to be ſeen, when thoſe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſons themſelves, whom <hi>Paul</hi> with an outragious fury perſecuted, were full of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and at leaſt many of them famous and renowned for their miracles. Neither did this bounty of Chriſt make a ſtand at <hi>Paul.</hi> For the Apoſtle himſelf ſheweth in the words that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that place to <hi>Timothy,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt would ſhew an example in him of all long ſuffering,</hi> that others alſo from thence might have a ſtrong be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of ſo great mercy of Chriſt towards them, If Chriſt did both beare with, in ſo great evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and clearneſſe of the truth, a blaſphemer, a perſecutor, and contumelious perſon, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſo great a favour upon him, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the moſt holy function of the Apoſtolicall office unto him, becauſe whatſoever he did, hee did it ignorantly, through unbeliefe: Why doe the ſervants of Ieſus Chriſt refuſe to tolerate thoſe, who at this time, wherein no man dares ſay the Chriſtian religion is attended with ſo great ſplendour and renowne of miracles, may erre indeed, and perhaps blaſpheme through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119385:38"/> yet for all that, perſecute no man, give reproachfull words to no man, nor trouble any man for religions ſake. But that it may yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more manifeſtly, by the example of Chriſt, that wee ought not to ſuppreſſe Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques by violence, and to haule them to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; let us obſerve how he behaved himſelfe towards Apoſtates. The Law, as we have ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified before, commands an Apoſtate to be ſlain without mercy: <hi>Thine eye ſhall not pity him, neither ſtalt thou ſhew mercy, nor keep him ſecret, But thou ſhalt even kill him, thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him to put him to death.</hi> Will not they ſay here, that hold it fit for Heretiques to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, that this courſe is a great deal rather to be taken againſt thoſe which revolt from Chriſt, and when they have been his diſciples, will now no longer be of their company? Certainly, if Heretiques were to be ſlain, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding profeſſe and honour the name of Chriſt, and are ready to ſuffer a moſt terrible and cruell death for his honour, although they do not rightly underſtand his doctrine: Much more ſhall they be worthy of this puniſhment, who altogether reject his doctrine, and do ſo forſake that faith which they had placed in him, that they will not profeſſe his name any longer, and be converſant amongſt his diſciples. But what, did Chriſt teach us by his example, that we ought ſo to do? and did he not rather demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the contrary? We read in <hi>John,</hi> c. 6. v. 66. that after Chriſt had diſcourſed much concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119385:39"/> the <hi>eating of his own fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking of his own blood;</hi> Many of his Diſciples being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this his ſpeech, went back, and walked no more with him. But what ſaith Chriſt to theſe things? Did he lead them violently to puniſhment, or thought it fit they ſhould? In no wiſe. Moreover he beſpake thoſe his twelve Diſciples or Apoſtles after this manner: <hi>Will ye alſo go away?</hi> as if ſo be he had given them liberty to go away, if they would. Thou wilt ſay, that Chriſt had no magiſtrate, nor people at his beck and command, to bring them to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But he had that divine vertue and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er dwelling in himſelf, by which he might be able to deſtroy them without any externall force. And to have done it in ſuch a way, would not have been ſo liable and obnoxious to blame and reprehenſion; becauſe a puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon them by a Divine vertue and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ought to be accounted by them as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted by God himſelf, and ſo to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged moſt juſt. Moreover, if ſuch a courſe had been taken in deſtroying them, the reſt of the Diſciples would have been ſtricken with ſo much the greater fear of daring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt from Chriſt, and his holy religion. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if thoſe Catholiques, who hold it fit for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques to be perſecuted and deſtroyed, could have deſtroyed them by their Anathema, as by a thunderbolt ſent miraculouſly from God, they would in no wiſe have forborne to do it: And it were to be deſired, not only by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119385:39"/> but even by the Heretiques themſelves in ſome reſpect, that Catholiques might be able to do it; becauſe from thence they would be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly convinced that the Catholique religion were true, and proceeded from God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would imbrace it preſently, neither would ſuffer ſuch a ſevere and powerfull thunderbolt to be darted forth upon them: and then no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique would fall into hereſie. Why then did not Chriſt do ſo, who had ſo great power to effect it? Was it not therefore, becauſe he judged it moſt averſe and disagreeable to his moſt gentle and meek ſpirit, and to the religion which he publiſhed, and to the purpoſe and will of God, for performance whereof he was ſent into the world? He came not, as elſwhere he ſpeaks of himſelf, to <hi>deſtroy mens lives,</hi> but to <hi>ſave them.</hi> Why therefore do not his ſervants and diſciples the like, before whom he ſets himſelf for an example to be imitated, who are or ought to be partakers of that Spirit, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe his moſt holy religion? They ought to call to memory that, which our Saviour himſelfe once anſwered to his diſciples, when the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans refuſed to entertain him: For when they asked him whether he would have them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that <hi>fire come down from heaven and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, even as Elias did?</hi> Jeſus rebuked them and ſaid, <hi>Ye know not of what ſpirit ye are, for the Son of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> That is, he would have his Diſciples to be as mild and gentle as himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119385:40"/>
            <p> Before we leave this Argument, we would have Catholiques to conſider, what men of great renown in former times amongſt the Doctors of the Catholike Church, thought concerning this matter, and what gentleneſſe they held fit to be uſed towards hereticks, whom they believed to be infected with moſt peſtilent and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous errors. After this manner <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writes concerning the Manichees: <hi>Let them exerciſe cruelty againſt you, who know not what a labour it is to find out the Truth, and what a difficulty it is to avoyd Errors. Let them exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe cruelty againſt you, who are ignorant what a rare and difficult thing it is to overcome carnall phantaſies, by the ſerenity and cleerneſſe of a pious mind. Let them excrciſe cruelty againſt you, who are ignorant, with how great difficulty the eye of the inward man is healed, that it may behold its own Sun. Let them exerciſe cruelty againſt you, who know not how great grones and ſighs muſt be uttered, before we can attain to ſome ſmall meaſure of the knowledge of God.</hi> Laſt of all, <hi>Let them exerciſe cruelty againſt you, who are deceived with no ſuch Error, as they perceive you to be deceived with. But I for my part can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exerciſe any cruelty againſt you, whom I ought ſo to bear with now, as I did then with my ſelf, and to deal with you in ſo great wiſdome, at my neighbours dealt with me, when I being out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and blind, erred in your Sect.</hi> But of the Arrians, <hi>Salvian</hi> Biſhop of the Maſſilian Church ſpeaketh in this wiſe: <hi>Hereticks they</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119385:40"/> 
               <hi>are, but unwittingly: in our eſteem they be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, not in their own; for they judge themſelves to be ſo much Catholikes, that they bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; defame us our ſelves with the title of Hereticall impiety; therefore what they are to us, that we are to them. We are ſure that they are injurious to the Divine generation, becauſe they ſay that the Son is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the Father: They think us injurious to the Father, becauſe we believe them to be equall. We are in the truth, but they preſume that they are. It is we that honour God; but they hold this to be the honour of God, which they believe. They are undutifull, but they hold this to be the chiefeſt duty of religion. They are ungodly, but they think it to be true piety. They erre therefore, but with a good mind, not through hatred, but believe that they do honour and love the Lord according to his own will and deſire: Although they have not a right faith, yet they account it to be a perfect love of God, to believe as they do. After what manner they ſhall be puniſhed, in the day of Judgment, for this very error of falſe opinion, none can know beſides the Judge. In the mean while God (as I believe) is patient toward them, becauſe he ſees that though they do not believe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, yet they erre with a mind and affection to be of a godly opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then the caſe is thus, any man ſeeth that Catholiques, in the cauſe of Heretiques, ought to follow that counſel of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> by which he ſometimes diſſwaded the Rulers of the Jewes from giving their cenſure, that violent hands
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119385:41"/> ſhould be laid upon the Apoſtles: of which matter we read in the <hi>Acts:</hi> for we read, that he thus beſpake his companions in office: <hi>Refrain your ſelves from theſe men, and let them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 5. 38.</note> 
               <hi>alone, for if this Counſell,</hi> or, <hi>this Worke be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, ye cannot deſtroy it, leſt ye be found even fighters againſt God.</hi> That counſell alſo of the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder is to be followed, who forbad his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants <hi>to pluck up the Tares, leſt the Wheat alſo chance to be pluckt up with them, but to ſuffer them to grow till harveſt.</hi> Let not the Wheat take authority unto it ſelf, of plucking up the Tares by violence. For the Tares alſo, which take themſelves to be the Wheat, will reſume authority to themſelves to pluck up the Wheat; and ſeeing the Tares grow up more plentifully then the Wheat in the world, which is a field rather fruitfull for Vice, then Vertue and Piety; the Tares will more likely enjoy this power, then the Wheat. But if there be ſuch, who think they have no cauſe to be afraid, leſt they be plucked up by the Tares, becauſe of their multitude, and ſtrength, eſtabliſhed by the courſe of ſo many Ages, wherewith they may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their adverſaries in religion; they ought for that very thing to ſuſpect themſelves, and to be afraid leſt they may chance to be of the number of the Tares, becauſe they flouriſh and grow up ſo plentifully for ſo many ages together in ſuch a barren field for vertue: and leſt they may chance to ſtray from the narrow &amp; ſtraight
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119385:41"/> path of ſalvation, which few find ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. For thus ſaith our Saviour; <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtraight gate, for it is the wide gate and broad way that leadeth to deſtruction, and many there are which go in thereat, becauſe the gate is ſtraight, and the way narrow that leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi> Yet furthermore, the uncertain courſes of humane affairs ſhould be conſidered; Who doth not ſee, that things of the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree are oftentimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umbled down and brought low, and things of low degree get up by little and little unto the higheſt; That things of great ſtrength, and confirmed by long continuance of time, are weakned; that weak things acquire ſtrength? Neither is it to be wondred at, when even thoſe things which we now admire for their greatneſſe and ſtrength, were formerly ſmall and weak, and riſing from ſmall beginnings arrived to this greatneſſe. Wherefore none of them who think it requiſite to pluck up the Tares, can promiſe himſelf a perpetuall triumph over them; but every one ought to be afraid, leſt what judgement he gives againſt them, the ſame alſo may be applied againſt himſelf. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no greater wiſdome, than by the counſel of the houſholder, to ſtay till the <hi>laſt harveſt,</hi> when both without any danger of Error, and without damage to the Wheat, the Tares, by command of the houſholder being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the Wheat, ſhall be caſt into the fire; when neither the name of Tares ſhall be given to the Wheat, nor the Tares take unto
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119385:42"/> themſelves either the name of the Wheat, or deceive the reapers with the ſhew and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance thereof. So by this means the Tares will have no occaſion by the deeds of the Wheat, to pluck up the Wheat by violence: If they ſhould nevertheleſſe uſe violence, then at length the Wheat ſcattered by violence will ſpread abroad his ſeeds the farther, and come forth more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, the Tares being by little and little ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, untill the harveſt at laſt bring a totall deſtruction upon them.</p>
            <p>But ſome Catholique will alleadge; Suppoſe it be ſo, that Catholiques ought to live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with Heretiques, Is there any neceſſity therefore that aſſurance be given them for their ſafety? We have hitherto both lived peaceably with them, and are ready to do ſo for the time to come; but we will not have any ſtatute or privilege to be publiſhed, or extant for their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. It is neither neceſſary for them that it ſhould be done, when as they enjoy peace without it, &amp; may enjoy it for the time to come: Neither is it much for our honour. For what? may they not put confidence in our promiſe, and our vertue and goodneſſe? May they not rely upon our friendſhip, or the obligations and bonds of conſanguinity and kindred?</p>
            <p>This that is alleadged might perhaps be of ſome moment, if ſo be Heretiques did not heare both threatnings uttered abroad by no ſmall number, nor no inferior ſort of Catholiques, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, nor ſee Proteſtations hurtful to their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119385:42"/> ſecurity, and perceive ſome mens endeavours tending to their overthrow, or to the limiting and ſtraitning of their liberty. If moreover examples both ancient and modern, in other Countries, and alſo evident and manifold expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of this very Age did not force them to fear ſuch like matters. Finally, if they had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered no injury for Religion ſake; if they had not ſeen in this very Kingdome, their Temples, ſome burnt with fire, others pulled down, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate mens houſes plundered alſo, ſome men ſlain, wounded, and violently dealt withall. Wherefore Heretiques do not in every point enjoy peace, neither can aſſuredly promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they ſhall enjoy it, unleſſe Catholiques give them a bond of aſſurance to confirm it: Verily even for that very cauſe it may juſtly be denied that they do enjoy peace, becauſe a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge is denied them for it; for that is no peace, to which ſecurity is wanting: but there is no ſecurity, ſo long as Catholiques refuſe to grant a priviledge and covenant unto Heretiques for their aſſurance in enjoying it, and whileſt many either do, or threaten many things which are altogether againſt their peace and tranquility. From whence it is to be underſtood, that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques do neither require a ſuperfluous matter, whileſt they deſire their Liberty may be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by a publique ſtatute, and more fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by ordaining puniſhments againſt break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the peace, and a Court of judicature and juſtice for the equall triall of both parties. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119385:43"/> do they deſire a thing which is diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Catholiques, but that which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and attended with a ſingular and exceeding great praiſe both of equity, moderation and humanity, and alſo of diſcretion and wiſdome: For what diſhonour is it for thee to oblige thy ſelfe by a publike promiſe, and a regiſtred law, That thou wilt do that matter, which thou mayeſt not only honeſtly do, but alſo art bound in equity to do? But that this matter of which we now diſcourſe, is of ſuch a nature, hath been already ſufficiently demonſtrated. But if ſo be the fear of Heretiques were even ſuperfluous, would it not be a mans duty in way of courteſie and charity to hinder and take away all occaſion of that vain, indeed, yet great fear of ſo many thouſands; and truly in ſuch a matter, which neither ought to be troubleſome and grievous unto thee, if thou haſt a deſire to live peaceably with them, neither coſt thee any labour or price. Why do not Catholiques grant them that, at their requeſt, which they may freely grant? By this means they will take away all occaſion of ſuſpition and diſtruſt, which are two great plagues and obſtructions to friendſhip, and the common-wealth; And will oblige all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques both to themſelves, and to their country, in which they ſee that they may live ſafely and ſecurely, and which they apprehend to be no ſtep-dame, which would expell them, but a mother. By this means they alſo will ingage them, That if in any country their power waxe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119385:43"/> great, to give again to Catholiques aſſurance that they ſhall receive no harm, &amp; to take good order for their ſecurity; for which they are by no law bound to provide, if Catholiques will not take order for their ſecurity: For he which refuſeth to give another man aſſurance of peace, and reſerves a power unto himſelf of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, when he ſhall find a fit opportunity to do it, leaves him in like manner the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge againſt himſelf; and amongſt whom there are no lawes and priviledges of Peace, the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and rights of War remaine common to both parties. <hi>But there is no ſafety in War: We all pray to thee (O GOD) for Pease.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
